旧金山
大卫森宠物店
- 好，麦克古德太太 - 好，丹尼尔斯小姐
Hello, Mrs. MacGruder. Oh, hello, Miss Daniels.
有见过这么多海鸥吗？ 想是怎么回事？
Have you ever seen so many gulls? What do you suppose it is?
一定是海上有暴风雨 把它们赶往内陆了
There must be a storm at sea. That can drive them inland, you know.
我还希望会晚点过来 鸟还没送到呢
I was hoping you'd be a little late. You see, he hasn't arrived yet.
- 但说三点的 - 我知道
- Oh, but you said 3:00. - Oh, I know.
我知道，我打了一早的电话
I know. I've been calling all morning.
丹尼尔斯小姐，有所不知
Oh, Miss Daniels, you have no idea.
它们很难弄到手，真的
They are so difficult to get. Really, they are.
我们得从印度进口雏鸟，然后…
We have to get them from India, when they're just baby chicks, and then...
这只不是雏鸟吧？
This one won't be a chick, will he?
当然不是 这只是成年的八哥鸟
Certainly not. Oh, no, certainly not. This will be a full-grown mynah bird. Full-grown.
- 它会说话？ - 它当然会…
And he'll talk? Well, yes, of course he'll...
不，得教它说话
Well, no, you'll have to teach him to talk.
我最好再打通电话 他们说三点会到
I guess maybe I'd better phone. They said 3:00.
可能是塞车吧，我联络看看
Maybe it's the traffic. I'll call.
- 能稍等一下吗？ - 还是把鸟送到我家吧
Would you mind waiting? Well, maybe you'd better deliver him.
我给我家的地址
Let me give you my address.
那好吧
Oh, well, all right,
但我确定他们在路上了
but I'm sure they're on the way.
我能打通电话吗？
Would you mind if I called?
请便
No. All right.
- 请帮个忙 - 什么？
I wonder if you could help me. What?
我说请帮个忙
I said, I wonder if you could help me.
- 是，你想找什么，先生？ - 爱情鸟
Yes. What is it you're looking for, sir? Lovebirds.
爱情鸟？
Lovebirds, sir?
是，我听说那有分很多种类
Yes. I understand there are different varieties.
- 是真的吗？ - 真的
Is that true? Well, yes, there are.
这是要给我妹妹当生日礼物的
Well, these are for my sister for her birthday, you see,
她才11岁 所以我不想买一对
and as she's only gonna be 11, I wouldn't want a pair of birds
过于热情的鸟
that were too demonstrative.
我完全理解
I understand completely.
但我也不想买一对太冷淡的鸟
At the same time, I wouldn't want them to be too aloof, either.
当然不了
No, of course not.
店里有相敬如宾的一对小鸟吗？
Do you happen to have a pair of birds that are just friendly?
应该有，我找找看
Oh, I think so. Now, then, let me see.
那些不是爱情鸟吗？
Aren't those lovebirds?
不，那些是红鸟
No. Those are red birds.
我以为它们是红雀
I thought they were strawberry finches.
对，我们也这样称呼它们
Yes. We call them that, too.
找到了，爱情鸟
Here we are. Lovebirds.
那是金丝雀
Those are canaries.
不觉得自己很糟糕吗？
Doesn't this make you feel awful?
什么很糟糕…
Doesn't what make me feel...
把这些可怜无辜的小东西 关在笼子里？
Having all these poor, little innocent creatures caged up like this?
我们总不能 让它们在店里飞来飞去吧
Well, we can't just let them fly around the shop, you know.
当然不能
No, I suppose not.
有什么鸟类学上的原因 必须把它们隔开吗？
Is there an ornithological reason for keeping them in separate cages?
有，为了保护品种
Well, certainly. It's to protect the species.
对，那很重要 尤其是在换毛期的时候
Yes, that's important, especially during the molting season.
那是特别危险的时期
That's a particularly dangerous time.
- 它们正在换毛吗？ - 一部分是
Are they molting now? Oh, some of them are.
怎么知道？
How can you tell?
它们会垂头丧气的
Well, they get a sort of hangdog expression.
我知道了，那爱情鸟呢？
Yes, I see. Well, what about the lovebirds?
你确定不看看金丝雀？
Are you sure you wouldn't like to see a canary instead?
我们这周进了些很美的金丝雀
We have some very nice canaries this week.
好吧
All right.
好，我能看看吗？
All right. May I see it, please?
怎么了？
Oh, what is it? Oh!
抓到了
There we are.
- 好险 - 太好了
- Oh, there. - Wonderful.
回的金牢笼吧 梅兰妮丹尼尔斯
Back in your gilded cage, Melanie Daniels.
你说什么？
What did you say?
我只是在打比喻，丹尼尔斯小姐
I was merely drawing a parallel, Miss Daniels.
- 你怎么知道我的名字？ - 小鸟告诉我的
How did you know my name? A little birdie told me.
再见，丹尼尔斯小姐、女士
Good day, Miss Daniels. Madam.
慢着，我不认识你
Hey, wait a minute. I don't know you.
- 但我认识 - 怎么说？
Ah, but I know you. How?
- 我们在法庭上见过 - 我们未曾在法庭上见过
We met in court. We never met in court or anyplace else.
没错，我换个说法 我在法庭看过
That's true. I'll rephrase it. I saw you in court.
什么时候？
When?
不记得因为的恶作剧
Don't you remember one of your practical jokes
使得一扇玻璃窗被打破了吗？
that resulted in the smashing of a plate-glass window?
- 我没有打破窗户 - 但是恶作剧害的
I didn't break that window. Yes, but your little prank did.
- 法官真该把关进大牢 - 你是谁，警察吗？
The judge should've put you behind bars. What are you, a policeman?
我不太相信法律，丹尼尔斯小姐 我也不太喜欢恶作剧
I merely believe in the law, Miss Daniels. And I'm not too keen on practical jokers.
- 那你的爱情鸟故事… - 我是真的想买爱情鸟
What do you call your lovebird story if not... Oh, I really wanted the lovebirds.
你明知道我不是店员，你故意…
Well, you knew I didn't work here. You deliberately...
对，我一进门就认出了
Right. I recognized you when I came in.
我只是想让知道 当被整的一方是什么感受
I just thought you might like to know what it's like to be on the other end of a gag.
- 有什么感想？ - 我认为你是个坏蛋
What do you think of that? I think you're a louse.
我是 再见，丹尼尔斯小姐、女士
I am. Good day, Miss Daniels. Madam.
真庆幸你没买到爱情鸟
And I'm glad you didn't get your lovebirds.
我会去别的地方买，法庭上见了
Oh, I'll find something else. See you in court.
- 那个人是谁？ - 我不知道
Who was that man? I have no idea.
他们说 八哥鸟今天下午就会送到
They said the mynah bird would be here later this afternoon,
若愿意再过来一趟
if you care to come back.
不，送到我家吧
No, you'd better send him.
- 能借用电话吗？ - 请便
May I use this phone? Why, certainly.
《每日新闻报》？ 我是 梅兰妮丹尼尔斯，请转地方新闻部
Daily News? It's Melanie Daniels. Could you get me the City Desk, please?
请留步，麦克古德太太
Just a minute, Mrs. MacGruder.
你好，查理，我是梅兰妮
Hello, Charlie. Melanie.
我要请你帮个忙
I want you to do a favor for me.
不，只是个小忙
No, this is a small one.
给你压力？ 亲爱的查理 我怎么会给你压力？
Pressure you? Why, Charlie, darling, would I try to pressure you?
你能替我致电汽车监理所吗？
Would you call the Department of Motor Vehicles for me?
找出这个车牌的车主
Find out who owns this license plate,
W-J-H-0-0-3 W-J-H-0-0-3.
对，加州车牌
Yes, a California plate.
不，我等会就过去 爸爸在办公室吗？
No. I'll stop off in a little while. Is Daddy in his office?
不，我不想打断会议 告诉他我晚点去找他
No, I don't want to break in on a meeting. Tell him I'll see him later.
谢谢你，查理
Thank you, Charlie.
店里有爱情鸟吗？
Do you have any lovebirds?
不，店里没有 但我可以替订购
Well, no, not in the shop, but I can order them for you.
- 多快会到？ - 什么时候要？
How soon? Well, when would you want them?
立刻
Immediately.
明天早上应该就能送到
Well, I could probably have them here by tomorrow morning.
- 那样可以吗？ - 当然可以
Would that be all right? That would be just fine.
米契尔班纳先生收
- 小姐，这是要给米契班纳的？ - 对
Miss, is that for Mitch Brenner? Yes.
- 他不在家 - 没关系
He's not home. That's all right.
如果要送小鸟给他 他要周一才会回来
He won't be back until Monday, I mean, if those birds are for him.
- 周一？ - 是
- Monday? - Yes.
我想不该把小鸟留在走廊上吧？
I don't think you should leave them in the hall, do you?
那…他去哪了？
Well... Where did he go?
博德加湾 他每个周末都会去那里
Bodega Bay. He goes there every weekend.
博德加湾在哪里？
Bodega Bay. Where's that?
沿着海岸往北走约一百公里
Up the coast, about 60 miles north of here.
一百公里…
Sixty...
走高速公路约一个半小时的车程 走海岸公路则要两小时
It's an hour and a half by freeway, or two hours if you take the Coast Highway. Oh.
我愿意照顾小鸟 但我也要出远门
I'd look after them myself, but I'm going away, too.
很抱歉
I'm awfully sorry.
邮局-  日用品
五金- 杂货
- 早安 - 早安
- Good morning. - Good morning.
- 我想请你帮个忙 - 我尽量
I wonder if you could help me. I'll try my best.
我要找米契尔班纳
I'm looking for a man named Mitchell Brenner.
- 你认识他吗？ - 认识
- Do you know him? - Yeah.
- 他住在哪里？ - 博德加湾
- Where does he live? - Right here, Bodega Bay.
- 博德加湾的哪里？ - 海湾对面
Yes, I know, but where? Right across the bay there.
哪里？
Where?
- 看见我指的方向了？ - 是
Now, see where I'm pointing? Yes.
看见那两棵大树了？
See them two big trees across there?
- 海湾的另一边吗？ 看见了 - 那栋白色房子？
On the other side of the bay? Yes. - And the white house?
- 是 - 那就是班纳家了
- Yes. That's where the Brenners live.
班纳家？ 班纳夫妇的家？
The Brenners? Mr. and Mrs. Brenner?
- 不，只有莉迪雅和两个孩子 - 两个孩子？
No. Just Lydia and the two kids. The two kids?
对，米契和小女儿
Yeah, Mitch and the little girl.
我懂了，我要怎么过去？
Oh, I see. How do I get down there?
沿着海湾边的路走 就能走到他们家大门口
You follow the road around the bay, and that'll take you right to their front door.
大门口，我能走小路吗？
The front door. Is there a back road I can take?
- 不，只有那条路 - 我想给他们惊喜
No. That's the only road. You see, I want to surprise them.
- 我不想让他们看见我 - 这样
I don't want them to see me arrive. Oh.
这是惊喜
It's a surprise, you see.
可以乘船穿过海湾 到他们家的码头
Well, you could get yourself a boat and cut right across the bay to their dock.
我要去哪租船？
Where would I get a boat?
下方的海潮餐厅
Down by the Tides Restaurant.
- 曾开过船吗？ - 当然
Did you ever handle an outboard boat? Of course.
- 我替叫船吧？ - 谢谢
Want me to order one for you? Well, thank you.
- 的名字？ - 丹尼尔斯
- What name? - Daniels.
好
Okay.
- 你能否告诉我… - 请稍等一下
I wonder if you could tell me... Yeah. Just hold it a minute, please.
- 小女儿的名字？ - 班纳家的小女儿？
The little girl's name? The little Brenner girl?
- 是 - 应该是爱丽丝吧
Yes. Alice, I think.
哈利，班纳家的小女儿 叫什么名字？
Harry, what's the little Brenner girl's name?
- 露薏丝 - 爱丽丝吗？
- Lois. - Alice, isn't it?
- 不，是露薏丝 - 是爱丽丝
No, it's Lois. It's Alice.
你确定吗？
Are you sure?
我不敢保证 如果是想问这个
Well, I'm not positive, if that's what you mean.
我需要她的真名
I need her exact name, you see.
请再稍等一下
Oh, just hold on one more minute, please.
这样的话，我教怎么做
In that case, I'll tell you what you do.
一路穿过镇上 会看见左手边有一间小旅馆
You go straight through town till you see a little hotel on your left.
然后右转
Then you turn right there.
- 记好了？ - 是
- Now, you got that? - Yes.
在靠近山顶处 会看见一所学校，再过去
Near the top of the hill, you'll see the school, and just beyond,
有一间信箱是红色的房子
a little house with a red mailbox.
那里是安妮海沃斯老师的家
That's where Annie Hayworth, the schoolteacher, lives.
- 可以问她班纳家小女儿的事 - 谢谢
You ask her about the little Brenner girl. Well, thank you.
替自己省点麻烦吧 我确定她叫爱丽丝
Save yourself a lot of trouble. Name's Alice for sure.
我20分钟后能搭船吗？
Can I have the boat in about 20 minutes?
- 电话费要多少？ - 不用了
How much for the phone calls? Oh, it's nothing.
谢谢
Thank you.
博德加湾学校
- 是谁？ - 我
Who is it? Me.
“我” 是谁？
Who's "me"?
- 海沃斯小姐？ - 是
- Miss Hayworth? - Yes.
我是梅兰妮丹尼尔斯 抱歉打扰了…
I'm Melanie Daniels. I'm sorry to bother you, but...
- 有事吗？ - 邮局的人要我来找
Yes? The man at the post office sent me.
他说知道班纳家小女儿的名字
He said you could tell me the name of the little Brenner girl.
凯西？
Cathy?
她住在海湾对面那间白色房子？
The one who lives in the white house across the bay?
- 没错，凯西班纳 - 他很确定是爱丽丝或露薏丝
That's the one. Cathy Brenner. He seemed sure it was either Alice or Lois.
所以这镇上的信 永远送不到对的地方
Which is why the mail never gets delivered to the right place in this town.
- 抱歉，要抽烟吗？ - 谢谢
I'm sorry. Smoke? Thank you.
找凯西有事吗？
Did you want to see Cathy about something?
没什么事
Well, not exactly.
是米契的朋友？
Are you a friend of Mitch's?
不算是
No, not really.
我20分钟前就想抽烟了
You know, I've been wanting a cigarette for the last 20 minutes.
但我一直闲不下来
I just couldn't convince myself to stop.
翻土这件事会让人停不下来
This tilling of the soil can become compulsive, you know.
这花园很漂亮
It's a very pretty garden.
谢谢 这是度过空闲时间的好方法
Oh, thank you. Well, it's something to do in your spare time.
在博德加湾，空闲时间可多了
There's a lot of spare time in Bodega Bay.
打算久留吗？
Are you planning on staying long?
不，只待几个小时
No, just a few hours.
见过凯西后就要离开？
Then you're leaving after you see Cathy?
差不多
Well, something like that.
抱歉，我无意 把自己搞得神秘兮兮的
I'm sorry. I don't mean to sound so mysterious.
这不关我的事
Actually, it's none of my business.
我最好该出发了
Well, I better be on my way.
- 非常谢谢 - 不客气
- Thank you very much. - Not at all.
从旧金山 沿海岸公路开车过来？
Did you drive up from San Francisco by the coast road?
对
Yes.
- 风景很棒吧 - 很漂亮
Nice drive. It's very beautiful.
你们在旧金山认识的？
Is that where you met Mitch?
对
Yes.
我想大家都是 在那里认识米契的
I guess that's where everyone meets Mitch.
海沃斯小姐，换神秘兮兮了
Now you sound a bit mysterious, Miss Hayworth.
是吗？
Do I?
我无意这么做 事实上，我没什么秘密
I don't mean to. Actually, I'm an open book, I'm afraid.
或者该说我高深莫测
Or, rather, a closed one.
- 真漂亮，这是什么鸟？ - 爱情鸟
Oh, pretty. What are they? Lovebirds.
我知道了 祝好运，丹尼尔斯小姐
I see. Good luck, Miss Daniels.
谢谢，我可以走这边吗？
Thank you. Can I get out this way?
右转吧 那会带回大马路上
Go right around. It'll take you back to the main road.
谢谢
Thank you.
海沃斯
凯西收
海潮餐厅- 快艇出租
- 丹尼尔斯小姐的船准备好了？ - 是的
Do you have a boat for Miss Daniels?
Yes, ma'am.
就是下方那一艘
It's the one right below.
- 没事吧？ - 我没事
- Are you all right? - Yes, I think so.
- 它怎么会攻击我？ - 那是我见过最吓人的鸟
What do you suppose made it do that? That's the damnedest thing I ever saw.
我不知道 它似乎是故意冲向的，流血了
I don't know. It seemed to swoop down at you deliberately. Oh, you're bleeding, too.
我们去擦药，好吗？
Let's take care of that. Okay?
乖女孩
That's a girl.
来吧
Come on.
米契，怎么了？
What happened, Mitch?
- 海鸥攻击她 - 海鸥？
- Gull hit her. - A gull?
去餐厅看看吧
Let's try up at the restaurant, all right?
可能需要打破伤风针
Might need a tetanus shot.
我在去年五月出国前 打过预防针了
I had a booster before I went abroad last May.
海潮餐厅
- 怎么了？ - 你好，迪克，这位小姐受伤了
What happened? Hello, Deke. Young lady cut herself.
- 我该找医生吗？ - 不，应该没那么严重，我看看
Shall I call a doctor? No, I don't think it's that serious. Let's see.
海伦，去拿些棉花和消毒药水
Helen, get some cotton and antiseptic.
小姐，在外头受伤的吗？
You cut yourself outside, miss?
别担心，迪克 她在船上受伤的
Don't worry, Deke. She did it in a boat.
曾有个男人在停车场摔倒
Well, I had a man trip and fall in the parking lot once.
眼也不眨一下就告我
Sued me before I could bat an eyelash.
丹尼尔斯小姐不会告人
I don't think Miss Daniels is gonna sue anybody.
拿去
Here.
- 你才是律师 - 谢谢
Well, you're the lawyer. Thank you.
- 那是什么？ - 双氧水
What's that? Just some peroxide.
我来清洗伤口
I'll clean out the cut.
你是律师啊
So you're a lawyer.
没错
That's right.
我通常是替人辩护 丹尼尔斯小姐，但若我要告人…
Of course, I usually defend people, Miss Daniels, but if I were prosecuting...
- 你在这里执业？ - 旧金山，来干嘛？
Do you practice here? Uh-uh. San Francisco. What are you doing up here?
- 专攻哪种法律？ - 刑法
What kind of law? Criminal.
所以你才想让每个人去坐牢？
Is that why you want to see everyone behind bars?
不是每个人
Oh, not everyone, Miss Daniels.
- 只有犯法和恶作剧的人 - 没错
Only violators and practical jokers. That's right.
抱歉
- Ow! - Oh, sorry.
- 刚在那里做什么？ - 你没看见爱情鸟？
What are you doing up here? Didn't you see the lovebirds?
是说大老远 替我送爱情鸟过来？
Oh, you mean, you came all this way to bring me those birds?
鸟是送给你妹妹的 你说她过生日
To bring your sister those birds. You said it was her birthday.
- 反正我原本就要过来 - 为什么？
Besides, I was coming up anyway. What for?
见我朋友，轻一点
To see a friend of mine. Careful.
抱歉，的朋友是谁？
Oh, sorry. Who's your friend?
安妮海沃斯，学校老师
Annie Hayworth, the schoolteacher.
安妮海沃斯
Annie Hayworth.
这世界真小
Well, small world.
是
Yes.
怎么认识安妮？
How do you know Annie?
我们上同一所大学
We went to school together, college.
是吗？ 真想不到 要在这里待多久？
Did you? Imagine that. How long are you staying up here?
这个周末
The weekend.
血差不多止住了 按着伤口吧
Well, I think the bleeding's almost stopped. Why don't you hold that on?
- 来拜访安妮？ - 对
So you came up to see Annie, huh? Yes.
我想是来看我的
I think you came up to see me.
我为什么要来看你呢？
Now, why would I want to see you of all people?
我不知道 但一定是大费周章地
I don't know, but you must've gone to a lot of trouble
调查我是谁和我住在哪里
to find out who I was and where I lived.
一点都不麻烦 我只需打给我父亲的报社
It was no trouble at all. I simply called my father's newspaper.
而且我原本就要过来 我已经说过了
Besides, I was coming up anyway. I've already told you that.
- 很喜欢我吧？ - 我讨厌你
You really like me, huh? I loathe you.
你没礼貌，既自大又骄傲…
You have no manners. You're arrogant, and conceited, and...
我本来写了封信要给你 但我撕掉了
I wrote you a letter about it, in fact, but I tore it up.
- 上头写了什么？ - 不关你的事
What did it say? None of your business.
我也不喜欢你的海鸥
I can't say I like your seagulls much, either.
- 我大老远过来… - 本来就要过来，记得吗？
I come all the way up here to... But you were coming up anyway, remember?
米契？
Mitch?
我看到你的车子 你到镇上做什么？
I thought I saw your car. What are you doing in town?
- 我来签收货物 - 什么？
I had to acknowledge a delivery. Of what?
妈妈，这是梅兰妮丹尼尔斯 丹尼尔斯小姐，这是我母亲
Mother, I'd like you to meet Melanie Daniels. Miss Daniels, my mother.
好吗？
How do you do?
好，丹尼尔斯小姐 签收什么？
How do you do, Miss Daniels? Acknowledge a what?
货物，丹尼尔斯小姐 从旧金山替我们送小鸟过来
A delivery. Miss Daniels brought us some birds from San Francisco.
做为凯西的生日礼物 她在哪里？
For Cathy for her birthday. Where is she?
她在布林梅尔家
Across at Brinkmeyer's.
事实上，丹尼尔斯小姐 要在这里过周末
As a matter of fact, Miss Daniels is staying up here for the weekend,
所以我已邀请她今晚一起用餐
so I've already invited her for dinner tonight.
不辞辛劳送那些鸟过来
Well, you did go to the trouble of bringing those birds.
没什么
Oh, I couldn't possibly.
- 你说鸟？ - 对，爱情鸟
You did say birds? Yes, lovebirds.
我知道了
Oh, I see.
所以我们可不能 不向道谢就让离开
So we couldn't let you get away without thanking you in some small way.
还没见到凯西 况且要在这里过周末
And you haven't met Cathy, and you are staying the weekend.
- 是，不过… - 会留下来吧？
Well, yes, but... Well, you are, aren't you?
- 没错，但… - 那就说定了
Certainly, but... Then it's all settled.
- 晚餐几点开动？ - 七点，一如往常
What time is dinner, Mother? 7:00, the same as usual.
- 我会去接，住在哪里？ - 当然是安妮家
I'll pick you up. Where are you staying? With Annie, of course.
当然了，我真笨 6点45分可以吗？
Oh, of course. How stupid of me. 6:45?
安妮可能另有计划 我得问问看
Annie may have made other plans. I'll have to see.
此外，我自己知道路
Besides, I can find my own way.
确定？ 不会再租船了？
You're sure now? You won't hire a boat or anything?
- 我确定 - 那七点见了
I'm sure. 7:00, then.
也许吧
Maybe.
我们会等，头还痛吗？
We'll be waiting for you. How's your head?
好多了，谢谢
Much better, thank you.
班纳太太，我只是被海鸥弄伤
A gull hit me, Mrs. Brenner, that's all.
- 嗨，找到她了？ - 是
Oh, hi. Did you find her all right? Yes, I did.
我想问…
I was wondering...
那块招牌
That sign there.
房间出租
我可以在这里住上一晚吗？
Do you suppose I could have the room for just a single night?
我打算长期出租…
I was planning on renting it for a longer time...
我会很感激
I would appreciate it.
我找过镇上其他地方，都客满了
I've tried everywhere in town. They're all full.
好吧，的行李在车上？
Well, all right. Got your bags in the car?
我得说真是实际
Well, it's utilitarian, I'll say that.
我刚在杂货店 买了一些过夜用品
I just picked up some things for the night at the general store.
我本来没打算久留
You see, I hadn't planned on staying very long.
我知道 发生了出乎意料的事？
Yes, I know. Did something unexpected come up?
对，能借用的电话吗？ 我想打电话回家
Yes. May I use your phone? I'd like to call home.
炉子上有咖啡
I just put some coffee on the stove.
它们都不停止迁徙的？
Don't they ever stop migrating?
好！
Hi!
- 丹尼尔斯小姐？ - 是
Miss Daniels? Yes.
小鸟好漂亮！
Oh, they're beautiful!
跟我想要的一样 那是一只公鸟和一只母鸟吗？
They're just what I wanted. Is there a man and a woman?
- 我都分不清楚 - 应该是
I can't tell which is which. Well, I suppose so.
- 好，安妮没安排计划？ - 没有
Hello there. Annie had no plans, huh? No.
很好，我们很高兴能过来 饿了吗？
Fine. We're very glad you could come. You hungry?
- 相当饿了 - 晚餐快煮好了
- Reasonably. - Dinner's just about ready.
我们刚去看鸡
We've been out back looking at the chickens.
它们好像有点不对劲
Something seems to be wrong with them.
那些鸡没有不对劲，米契
There's nothing wrong with those chickens, Mitch.
- 我去打电话给佛莱德布林梅尔 - 那又能怎样？
I'm going to call Fred Brinkmeyer right now. What good's that gonna do?
鸡都不吃饲料
The chickens won't eat.
是他卖饲料给我的，不是吗？
He sold the feed to me, didn't he?
买者自负，妈妈 “货物既出恕不退换”
Caveat emptor, Mother. "Let the buyer beware."
你站在谁那边？
Whose side are you on?
- 我只是在引述法条 - 别管什么法条了
Merely quoting the law, dear. Never mind the law.
这不会太久，丹尼… 喂，佛莱德？ 我是莉迪雅班纳
This won't take long, Miss... Hello, Fred? Lydia Brenner.
- 我没打扰到你吃晚饭吧？ - 喝一杯吗？
- I didn't interrupt your dinner, did I? - How about a drink?
- 好的，谢谢 - 佛莱德，你卖给我不好的饲料
Thank you, I'd love one. Fred, that feed you sold me is no good.
鸡饲料
The chicken feed.
品质不好，鸡都不吃
Well, it's just no good. The chickens won't eat it.
鸡随时都是饿的
They're always hungry.
我到家后，开了一袋饲料 它们连碰都不碰
I opened a sack for them when I got home, and they just wouldn't touch it.
你懂鸡，我也懂 鸡不吃饲料
You know chickens as well as I do, and when they won't eat,
那一定就是饲料有问题，就这样
there's something wrong with what they're being fed. That's all.
不，它们不是挑嘴鸡
No, they're not fussy chickens.
谁？ 跟他有何关系？
Who? What's he got to do with it?
- 这是你父亲？ - 请坐
Is that your father? Mmm-hmm. Please sit down.
佛莱德，我不管 你卖了多少袋饲料给他，我的鸡…
Fred, I don't care how many sacks of feed you sold him. My chicken...
我知道了
Oh, I see.
丹佛西特
Dan Fawcett.
今天下午？ 那证实了我的话！ 你卖给我们的饲料…
This afternoon? Well, that just proves what I'm saying! The feed you sold us...
我最好去问问他
Well, maybe I'd better go over and see him.
你不会以为这是什么传染病吧？
You don't think there's something going around, do you?
才不是！
No, never!
不，佛莱德 它们没生病，只是不吃饲料
No, Fred, they don't seem sick at all. They just won't eat.
我会去找他，也许他…
Well, I'll try to go over and see him. Maybe he...
好吧，谢谢
All right. Thanks.
丹佛西特稍早也打过电话
He had a call from Dan Fawcett a while ago.
他的鸡也不吃饲料
His chickens won't eat either.
如所说，妈妈 布林梅尔先生卖的饲料不佳
It's what you said, Mom. Mr. Brinkmeyer's feed is no good.
不，凯西 他卖给佛西特先生的是另个牌子
No, Cathy. He sold Mr. Fawcett a different brand.
米契，你觉得是鸡生病了吗？
You don't think they're getting sick, do you, Mitch?
我还是搞不懂 怎么知道我想要爱情鸟
I still don't understand how you knew I wanted lovebirds.
哥哥告诉我的
Your brother told me.
跟米契在旧金山认识的？ 没错吧？
Then you knew Mitch in San Francisco? Is that right?
不算是
No, not exactly.
米契在旧金山认识很多人
Mitch knows a lot of people in San Francisco.
当然，他们多半是罪犯
Of course, they're mostly hoods.
- 凯西！ - 妈，他是最先承认的人
Cathy! Well, Mom, he's the first to admit it.
他大半天都待在法院里的拘留室
He spends half his day in the detention cells at the Hall of Justice.
凯西，在民主国家 人人都有公平受审的权力
In a democracy, Cathy, everyone is entitled to a fair trial.
- 哥的工作… - 妈，别说了！
Your brother's practice... Oh, Mom, please!
我知道民主那套狗屁 但他们还是罪犯
I know all that democracy jazz. They're still hoods.
他的一位委托人 朝老婆的头开了六枪
He has a client now who shot his wife in the head six times.
六枪！能想像吗？
Six times! Can you imagine it?
开两枪就很夸张了 不觉得吗？
I mean, even twice would be overdoing it, don't you think?
- 他为什么杀她？ - 他当时正在看球赛转播
Why did he shoot her? He was watching a ball game on television.
- 什么？ - 他老婆把电视转台
What? His wife changed the channel.
- 明天会参加我的生日会吗？ - 不会
Are you coming to my party tomorrow? I don't think so.
我得回旧金山
I have to get back to San Francisco.
- 不喜欢我们？ - 亲爱的，我当然喜欢
Don't you like us? Oh, darling, of course I do.
- 不喜欢博德加湾？ - 我还不知道
Don't you like Bodega Bay? I don't know yet.
米契很喜欢这里 他每个周末都过来
Mitch likes it very much. He comes up every weekend, you know,
虽然他在市区有间自己的公寓
even though he has his own apartment in the city.
他说旧金山就像桥墩上的蚁丘
He says San Francisco's like an anthill at the foot of a bridge.
旧金山偶尔是有点忙乱
I suppose it does get a little hectic at times.
若决定来我的生日会 别说是我告诉的
Well, if you do decide to come, don't say I told you about it.
这本该是一场惊喜派对
It's supposed to be a surprise party.
他们设计了很复杂的计划
You see, they've got this whole complicated thing figured out,
我下午会去蜜雪儿家玩
where I'm going over to Michele's for the afternoon,
但蜜雪儿的妈妈会说她头痛
and Michele's mother will say that she has a headache.
我是否愿意让她带我回家？
Would I mind very much if she took me home?
我一到家之后 所有的小孩都会跳出来！
Then when I get home here, all the kids will jump out!
不来吗？ 拜托来嘛？
Oh, won't you come? Won't you please come?
我没办法
I don't think so.
- 米契，她很迷人，不是吗？ - 是
She's a charming girl, isn't she, Mitch? Hmm? Yes.
非常漂亮
Certainly pretty. Mmm-hmm.
- 你跟她认识多久了？ - 我说过了，我们昨天才认识
How long have you known her? Now, I told you, dear, we met yesterday.
- 在鸟店里 - 在鸟店里
In a bird shop. In a bird shop.
她是鸟店的店员？
She was selling birds?
不，我只是让她相信 我以为她是店员，然后…
No, no. I just led her into believing that I believed she was, and then...
过程很复杂
Well, it's all very complicated.
但她确实买了爱情鸟 还大老远开车过来
But she did buy the lovebirds, and then drove all the way out here.
- 妈妈 - 怎么？
- Mother. - Yes?
上哪间法学院？
Where did you go to law school?
抱歉
Forgive me.
我只是对那样的女孩很好奇
I suppose I'm just naturally curious about a girl like that.
她很有钱吧？
She's very rich, isn't she?
应该是
Yeah, I suppose so.
她的父亲 是旧金山最大报社的合伙人
Her father's part owner of one of the big newspapers in San Francisco.
你还以为 他能让她的名字不见报
You'd think he could manage to keep her name out of print.
她时常登上报纸的八卦专栏
She's always mentioned in the columns, Mitch.
我知道
Yes, I know.
她就是去年在罗马 跳进喷水池的人，对吧？
She is the one who jumped into a fountain in Rome last summer, isn't she?
是
Yes.
我是有点老古板
I supposed I'm old-fashioned.
我知道那里的天气很温暖，但…
I know it was supposed to be very warm there, but...
事实上，报纸写说 她当时是一丝不挂
Well, actually, the newspapers said she was naked.
我知道，妈妈
Yes, I know, dear.
这当然不关我的事 但你带这样的女孩…
Of course, it's none of my business, but when you bring a girl like that...
- 妈妈？ - 是？
Darling? Yes?
我能自己应付梅兰妮丹尼尔斯
I think I can handle Melanie Daniels by myself.
只要你知道 你要的是什么就好，米契
Well, as long as you know what you want, Mitch.
我很清楚我要什么
I know exactly what I want.
- 能自己开车回去？ - 当然
Be able to find your way back all right? Oh, yes.
- 我能再见吗？ - 旧金山离这里很远
Will I be seeing you again? San Francisco's a long way from here.
我一周有五天待在旧金山 而且我时间很多
I'm in San Francisco five days a week with a lot of time on my hands.
我想见
I'd like to see you.
我们可以一起去游泳 妈妈告诉我喜欢游泳
Maybe we could go swimming or something. Mother tells me you like to swim.
- 令堂怎么知道我的兴趣？ - 我们都读同一篇八卦专栏
How does Mother know what I like to do? I guess we read the same gossip column.
那个啊，罗马
Oh, that. Rome.
我很喜欢游泳 我们应该处得来
Yeah, I really like to swim. I think we might get along very well.
以防你有兴趣知道 我是被推进喷水池的
In case you're interested, I was pushed into that fountain.
全身赤裸？
Without any clothes on?
我当时衣着整齐 写那篇报导的报社
With all my clothes on. The newspaper that ran that story
刚好是我父亲的竞争对手
happens to be a rival of my father's paper.
只是可怜无辜 被牵连的受害者？
You were just a poor, innocent victim of circumstances?
我不可怜也不无辜
I'm neither poor nor innocent,
但事实是…
but the truth of that particular...
事实是 跟一群狐群狗党混在一起？
The truth is, you're running around with a pretty wild crowd, isn't it?
那倒是真的 但我被推进喷水池
Yes, that's the truth, but I was pushed into that fountain,
也是事实
and that's the truth, too. Uh-huh.
真的认识安妮海沃斯？
Do you really know Annie Hayworth?
不，我来到这里才认识她
No. At least I didn't until I came up here.
- 所以们不是同学？ - 不是
- So you didn't go to school together? - No.
- 不是来看她？ - 不是！
- And you didn't come up here to see her? - No!
- 说谎！ - 对，我说谎
- You were lying! - Yes, I was lying.
有写信给我也是骗人的？
What about the letter you wrote me? Is that a lie, too?
我真的有写
No, I wrote the letter.
- 内容是什么？ - 上面写：亲爱的班纳先生
Well, what did it say? It said, "Dear Mr. Brenner.
“我想你需要这对爱情鸟 它们能改善你的人品”
"I think you need these lovebirds after all. "They may help your personality."
- 就这样 - 但撕掉了？
- That's what it said. - But you tore it up?
- 对 - 为什么？
- Yes. - Why?
因为这似乎太愚蠢了
Because it seemed stupid and foolish.
- 跟跳进罗马的喷水池一样 - 我解释过了！
Like jumping into a fountain in Rome. I told you what happened!
以为我会相信？
You don't expect me to believe that, do you?
我才不在乎你信不信！
Oh, I don't give a damn what you believe!
- 我还是想见 - 为什么？
- I'd still like to see you. - Why?
应该会很有趣
I think it might be fun.
那在罗马也许是个好理由 但现在不是了
That might've been good enough in Rome, but it's not good enough now.
- 我觉得是 - 我不觉得
- It is for me. - Well, not for me.
- 要什么？ - 我以为你早知道了
What do you want? I thought you knew.
我想要一丝不挂 跳进喷水池里，晚安
I want to go through life jumping into fountains naked. Good night.
- 丹尼尔斯小姐，是吗？ - 是
Miss Daniels, is that you? Yes.
嗨
Hi.
怎么了吗？ 伤口开始痛了？
Is something wrong? Is that cut beginning to bother you?
不，让我烦恼的不是伤口
No, it's not the cut that's bothering me.
- 要喝点白兰地吗？ - 若有的话，我想喝
Would you like some brandy? If you have some, I'd love it.
我去拿 请坐，丹尼尔斯小姐
I'll get it. Why don't you sit down, Miss Daniels?
想要穿件毛衣或盖件被子吗？
Oh, would you like a sweater or something, a quilt?
不用了，谢谢
No. No, thank you.
- 叫我梅兰妮就好 - 没问题
Won't you call me Melanie? All right.
谢谢
Thank you.
这里的晚上偶尔会有点冷
Gets a bit chilly here at night sometimes,
尤其是靠近海湾的地方
especially if you're over near the bay.
今晚过得如何？
Well, how did your evening go?
见到莉迪雅了？
Did you meet Lydia?
还是希望我换个话题？
Or would you rather I changed the subject?
也好
I think so.
- 喜欢这个小村庄吗？ - 我恨死了
Well, how do you like our little hamlet? I despise it.
这里对一般游客没什么魅力
Well, I suppose it doesn't offer much to the casual visitor,
除非对山坡上 一整排的小木屋有兴趣
unless you're thrilled by a collection of shacks on a hillside.
得花点时间习惯
It takes a bit of getting used to.
- 安妮，是哪里人？ - 旧金山
Where are you from originally, Annie? San Francisco.
那怎么会来到这里？
How did you happen to come up here?
很久以前 有个朋友邀请我到这里过周末
A friend invited me up for a weekend a long time ago.
我想也没什么理由好遮掩的
Look, I see no reason for being coy about this.
那个人是米契班纳 应该早就知道了
It was Mitch Brenner. I guess you knew that anyway.
跟我猜的一样
I suspected as much.
不用担心
Well, you needn't worry.
我们老早就分得一干二净
It's been over and done with a long time ago.
安妮，班纳先生跟我之间 什么都没有
Annie, there's nothing between Mr. Brenner and me.
没有吗？
Isn't there?
也许没有吧
Well, maybe there isn't.
或许米契跟任何女孩之间 都未曾有过什么
Maybe there's never been anything between Mitch and any girl.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
我也喝点酒好了
I think I'll have some of that.
我在旧金山时跟他走得很近
I was seeing a lot of him in San Francisco.
某个周末 他邀我和莉迪雅见面
Then one weekend, he invited me up to meet Lydia.
什么时候？
When was this?
四年前，他父亲过世后不久
Oh, four years ago, shortly after his father died.
- 当然，现在的情况可能不同了 - 不同？
Of course, things may be different now. Different?
莉迪雅啊
With Lydia.
- 她有点冷淡吧？ - 一点点
Did she seem a trifle distant? A trifle.
那情况可能没什么变
Well, then perhaps things aren't quite so different.
她的态度差点害我发疯
You know, her attitude nearly drove me crazy.
我回到旧金山后 花了好几天想弄清楚 我到底哪里得罪她了
When I got back to San Francisco, I spent days trying to figure out exactly what I'd done to displease her.
- 做了什么？ - 什么都没有
Well, what had you done? Nothing.
我只是出现了，原因呢？ 一个善妒的女人？
I simply existed. So what's the answer? A jealous woman, right?
占有欲很强的母亲？
A clinging, possessive mother?
错了
Wrong.
说是恋母情结 我看倒也不是那回事
With all due respect to Oedipus, I don't think that was the case.
那是什么原因？
Then what was it?
莉迪雅喜欢我 那才是最奇怪的地方
Lydia liked me. That's the strange part.
现在我已不再是威胁 我们竟成了好朋友
Now that I'm no longer a threat, we're very good friends.
- 那她当时为何不接受？ - 因为她害怕
Then why did she object to you? Because she was afraid.
害怕夺走米契？
Afraid you'd take Mitch?
害怕我对米契的付出
Afraid I'd give Mitch.
我不懂
I don't understand.
害怕任何女人能给米契 莉迪雅唯一能给他的东西，爱
Afraid of any woman who would give Mitch the one thing Lydia can give him, love.
那就算是 一个善妒和占有欲很强的女人
That adds up to a jealous, possessive woman.
我不这么想
No, I don't think so.
她并不害怕失去米契
You see, she's not afraid of losing Mitch.
她只害怕被抛弃
She's only afraid of being abandoned.
某人得告诉她 她也会因此多一个女儿
Someone ought to tell her she'd be gaining a daughter.
不，她已经有个女儿了
No. She already has a daughter.
那米契呢？ 他都没有表示意见？
Well, what about Mitch? Didn't he have anything to say about this?
我能理解他的立场
Well, I can understand his position.
他父亲死后 他跟莉迪雅过得很辛苦
He'd just been through a lot with Lydia after his father died.
他可不想再重来一次
He didn't want to risk going through it all again.
我懂了
Oh, I see.
所以我们分手了 当然不是立刻
So it ended. Not right then, of course.
我们回到旧金山后 偶尔还是会见面
We went back to San Francisco, saw each other now and then,
但我们都知道这结束了
but we both knew it was over.
那为何搬到博德加湾？
Then what are you doing here in Bodega Bay?
我想留在米契身边
I wanted to be near Mitch.
我知道我们分手了，但是…
Oh, it was over and done with, and I knew it, but...
我仍想留在他身边
I still wanted to be near him.
我还是很喜欢他
You see, I still like him a hell of a lot,
我不想失去这段友情
and I don't want to lose that friendship, ever.
喂
Hello.
你好
不，我还没睡
No, no, no, I wasn't asleep.
对，不久之前
Yes, just a little while ago.
当然，稍等
Sure. Hold on.
米契打来的
It's Mitch.
他要找
For you.
喂？ 对，我是梅兰妮
Hello? Oh, yes, this is Melanie.
很好，谢谢
Fine, thank you.
一点都不难 我只是沿着马路开
No, no trouble at all. I simply followed the road.
没必要道歉
Well... there's no need to apologize.
我能理解
I can understand.
你人真好，不，我没生气
That's very kind of you. No, I'm not angry.
我没办法，我得回旧金山
Well, I couldn't. I have to get back to San Francisco.
我不想让凯西失望，不过…
No, I wouldn't want to disappoint Cathy, but...
我知道了
I see.
好吧，我会到场
All right. Yes, I'll be there.
晚安，米契
Good night, Mitch.
他要我明天下午 参加凯西的生日会
He wants me to go to Cathy's party tomorrow afternoon.
我答应了
I said I would.
一定会很好玩
It should be fun.
我也会去帮忙
I'll be there, too, to help.
这真是没必要
Oh, it seems so pointless.
我要去睡觉了 今天真是漫长
Well, I think I'll go to sleep. It's been a busy day.
我的行李
My luggage.
真漂亮，在哪买的？ 布林梅尔的店？
That's pretty. Where'd you get that? Brinkmeyer's? Mmm.
认为我该参加吗？
Do you think I should go?
这要由决定
Well, that's up to you.
不，这得由莉迪雅决定吧？
No, it's really up to Lydia, isn't it?
别管莉迪雅了，想去吗？
Never mind Lydia. Do you want to go?
想
Yes.
- 那就去吧 - 谢谢，安妮
Then go. Thank you, Annie.
会是谁啊
Wonder who that can be.
有人吗？
Is someone there?
- 是谁？ - 看
Who is it? Look.
真可怜，可能是天色太暗迷路了
Poor thing. Probably lost his way in the dark.
但天色不暗，安妮
But it isn't dark, Annie.
今晚是满月
There's a full moon.
凯西，非常好
Cathy, that's very good. Very good.
开始吧
Okay. Here we go.
做得好，别让他抓到了
Attagirl. Come on. Don't let him get you.
我不能再喝了，我还要开车
No, I really shouldn't have any more. I'm driving.
事实上，我想请留下来吃晚饭
Well, actually, I'm trying to get you to stay for dinner.
还剩下很多烤牛肉
A lot of roast beef left over.
- 我不行，我得回家了 - 好吧
No, I couldn't possibly. I have to get back. All right.
- 干杯 - 干杯
- Cheers. - Cheers.
到底为什么要急着走？ 旧金山有要紧的事吗？
Seriously, why do you have to rush off? What's so important in San Francisco?
我明天早上还得工作
Well, I have to get to work tomorrow morning, for one thing.
- 有工作？ - 我有很多工作
You have a job? I have several jobs.
- 什么工作？ - 我有各式各样的工作
What do you do? I do different things on different days.
比如说？
Like what?
我周一和周三 在机场的旅客服务柜台工作
Well, on Mondays and Wednesdays, I work for the Travelers' Aid at the airport.
协助旅客？
Helping travelers?
不，是去误导他们 我以为你了解我的个性
No, misdirecting them. I thought you could read my character.
周二我在柏克莱大学 修读普通语义学的课程
On Tuesdays, I take a course in General Semantics at Berkeley,
寻找新的脏话
finding new four-letter words.
- 那不算工作… - 是说不必…
- That's not a job, of course... - You mean, you don't have to...
周四我要开会和出席午餐会
And on Thursdays, I have my meeting and lunch.
我猜是在地狱吧
In the underworld, I suppose.
恐怕要让你失望了
I shall disappoint you.
我们要帮助 一个韩国小男孩去上学
We're sending a little Korean boy through school.
我们正在为此募款
We actually raise money for it.
罗马的事…
You see, Rome...
那一整个夏天，我只顾着…
That entire summer, I did nothing but...
罗马很容易让人迷失
Well, it was very easy to get lost there.
回国之后，我认为我该开始…
So when I came back, I thought it was time I began...
重新寻找某些东西
Oh, I don't know, finding something again.
所以周一到周四 我让自己保持忙碌
So, on Mondays and Thursdays, I keep myself busy.
- 那周五呢？ - 周五？ 没事
What about Fridays? Fridays? They're free.
我偶尔会在周五到鸟店逛逛
I sometimes go to bird shops on Fridays.
我很高兴会去
I'm very glad you do.
美好天真的一天
A nice, innocent, little day.
当然
Oh, yes.
我有个泰莎姑妈 你有姑妈吗？
I have an Aunt Tessa. Have you got an Aunt Tessa?
我的姑妈拘谨又古板
Mine is very prim and straight-laced.
等她从欧洲回来后 我要送她一只八哥鸟
I'm giving her a mynah bird when she comes back from Europe.
八哥鸟会说话 如果这只鸟会说几个
Mynah birds talk, you know. Can you see my Aunt Tessa's face,
我在柏克莱学到的词 你能想像泰莎姑妈的表情吗？
when this one tells us one or two of the words I've picked up at Berkeley?
需要一点母亲的关爱，孩子
You need a mother's care, my child.
- 我不需要我母亲的爱 - 很抱歉
Not my mother's. Oh, I'm sorry.
你有什么好抱歉的？
What have you got to be sorry about?
我的母亲？ 别浪费时间了
My mother? Don't waste your time.
我11岁时，她抛弃我们 跟一个东部的饭店员工跑了
She ditched us when I was 11 and ran off with some hotel man in the east.
你知道什么是母爱？
You know what a mother's love is?
- 我知道 - 你是指被抛弃比较好？
Yes, I do. You mean it's better to be ditched?
不，有母亲的爱比较好 再也没见过她了？
No. I think it's better to be loved. Don't you ever see her?
我不知道她在哪里
I don't know where she is.
我还是去找孩子们玩吧
Well, maybe I ought to go join the other children.
开始吧，一…
All right. Here we go. One...
二…
Two...
三…
Three...
走吧
There you go.
你们看！
Look! Look!
嘿！不准碰我！
Hey! No touching allowed!
帮我把孩子们带进屋里
Help me get the children into the house.
进去吧
There you go.
米契，它们离开了吗？
Have they gone, Mitch?
- 离开了 - 有人受伤吗？
I think so. Is anyone hurt?
珍妮的脸颊被抓伤，但无大碍
Jenny got a scratch down her cheek, but it's nothing.
这是第三次了
That makes three times.
米契，这很不寻常吧？
Mitch, this isn't usual, is it?
昨天在船上攻击我的海鸥 昨晚在安妮家也有一只，现在…
The gull when I was in the boat yesterday, the one at Annie's last night, and now...
昨晚？ 什么意思？
Last night? What do you mean?
有只海鸥撞上安妮家的大门 米契，怎么回事？
A gull smashed into Annie's front door. Mitch, what's happening?
我不知道，得回安妮家吗？
I don't know. Do you have to go back to Annie's?
不，我的行李都在车上
No. I have my things in the car.
在回去之前 留下来吃点东西吧，我会安心点
Stay and have something to eat before you start back. I'd feel a lot better.
- 要加芥末吗？ - 不用，谢谢
Would you like some mustard with that? No, thank you.
安妮为何不留下来？
Why didn't Annie stay for dinner?
她说她要回家 接她妹妹从东部打来的电话
Said something about going home to take a call from her sister in the east.
它们怎么了？
What's the matter with them?
- 这些鸟是怎么了？ - 咖啡要放在哪里？
What's the matter with all the birds? Where did you want this coffee?
- 放在桌上，亲爱的 - 你动作快一点，米契
Here on the table, honey. Hurry up with yours, Mitch.
丹尼尔斯小姐一定很想上路了
I'm sure Miss Daniels wants to be on her way.
今晚该留下来，梅兰妮
I think you ought to stay the night, Melanie.
楼上有一间多出来的房间
We have an extra room upstairs and everything.
晚上的路况也很糟糕
That road can be a pretty bad one at night, too.
若我开到圣塔罗沙
If I go across to Santa Rosa,
就能早一点上高速公路 不是吗？
I'll come out on the freeway much earlier, won't I?
对，走高速公路快多了
Yes, and the freeway is much quicker.
但她会碰上 返回旧金山的大量车潮
But she'll be hitting all the heavy traffic going back to San Francisco.
那对爱情鸟叫得好厉害
Just listen to those lovebirds.
米契
Mitch.
遮住脸和眼睛！
Cover your faces! Cover your eyes!
这是麻雀
That's a sparrow, all right.
- 我们知道，艾尔 - 你们当时有点灯吗？
We know what it is, Al. Did you have a light burning or something?
有，但灯光 不至于会从烟囱传出去
Yes, but there wouldn't have been that much light going up the chimney.
鸟有时会被灯光吸引 但这情况确实少见
'Cause sometimes birds are attracted by light, you know. Sure is a peculiar thing.
但我们得想个办法解决！
Well, all right, but we've got to do something about it!
我不懂你的意思，米契 解决什么？
I don't think I get you, Mitch. Do about what?
鸟入侵房子
Well, the birds invaded the house.
应该是它们进到屋里后 惊慌失措了，如此而已
What's more likely, they got in the room and was just panicked. That's all.
我知道鸟在密闭的空间里会惊慌
All right, I'll admit a bird will panic in an enclosed room,
但它们不是不小心飞进来 而是从烟囱飞下来的
but they didn't just get in. They came in, right down the chimney.
我老婆曾在她的汽车后座上 发现一只鸟
My wife found a bird in the back seat of her car once.
跟他说生日会上的事
Tell him about the party.
没错，今天下午 我们在家举办凯西的生日会
That's right. We had a party here this afternoon for Cathy, for her birthday.
- 她几岁了？ - 11岁！生日会开到一半
How old is she? Eleven! In the middle of the party,
几只海鸥冲向孩子们！
some seagulls came down at the children!
丹尼尔斯小姐 昨天才被一只海鸥攻击
Miss Daniels was attacked by a gull only yesterday.
是，孩子们打扰那些鸟了吗？
Yeah. Were the kids bothering the birds or something?
因为你要是在它们周围捣乱
'Cause if you make any kind of a disturbance near them,
它们就会追你
they'll just come after you.
艾尔，孩子们当时在玩游戏 海鸥就攻击了
Al, the children were playing a game. Those gulls attacked.
莉迪雅，不觉得 用 “攻击” 太严重了吗？
Now, Lydia, "attack" is a pretty strong word, don't you think?
海鸥不会无故攻击人类
I mean, birds just don't go around attacking people
懂我的意思吗？
without no reason. You know what I mean?
大概是孩子吓到它们了
The kids probably scared them, that's all.
这些鸟攻击我们
These birds attacked.
我承认这屋子是被搞得一团乱
You got quite a mess here, I'll admit that.
你也许该在烟囱口加片纱网
Maybe you ought to put some screen on top of your chimney.
- 需要人手帮忙清理吗？ - 不用了
You want some help cleaning up? No. I can handle it.
清理起来应该不难
It shouldn't be too much of a job.
我带凯西去睡觉
I'll take Cathy up to bed.
我想我该留下，你觉得呢？
I think I should stay, don't you?
那再好不过了
It would be nice if you could.
我的行李在车上
My things are in the car.
- 跟我来吧？ - 好
- Do you want to go with me? - All right.
- 米契，还需要我帮忙吗？ - 不，谢了，艾尔
Well, anything else I can do, Mitch? No, thanks, Al.
- 我们没问题的 - 晚安，莉迪雅
We'll be all right. Good night, Lydia.
确实很奇怪
Sure is peculiar.
米契！
Mitch. Mitch. Mitch!
- 妈，什么事？ - 我送凯西去上学
Yes, Mother? I'm going to drop Cathy off now.
我也许会去佛西特农场看看
I'll probably drive over to the Fawcett farm.
好
Okay.
早安
Morning.
早安，乔治 佛西特先生在吗？
Good morning, George. Is Mr. Fawcett around?
他在，女士
I think so, ma'am.
今早还没看到他 但他应该在家里
Ain't seen him this morning, but he ought to be in there.
谢了
Thanks.
丹，你在家吗？
Dan, are you home?
妈妈！
Mother!
怎么了？ 怎么回事？
What is it, dear? What's the matter?
艾尔马龙副警长刚来过电话 他要我过去佛西特家
Al Malone, the deputy, just called. He wants me over at the Fawcett place.
圣塔罗沙的警探会赶到那里
Some detectives from Santa Rosa will be there.
- 没问题吧？ - 是
- Will it be all right? - Yes.
我只是要替母亲泡点茶
I was just taking your mother in some tea.
请小心点
Oh, be careful, please.
也小心点
And you be careful.
米契？
Mitch?
是我，班纳太太
No, it's me, Mrs. Brenner.
- 我认为会想喝点茶 - 谢谢
I thought you might like some tea. Oh. Thank you.
米契在哪里？
Where's Mitch?
艾尔马龙要他去佛西特农场一趟
Al Malone wanted him out at the Fawcett farm.
为什么？ 艾尔不相信我的说词？
Why? Didn't Al believe my story?
他从农场打电话过来的
He was calling from the farm.
- 他看见了 - 一定是
Then he saw. Oh, he must have.
他们找来圣塔罗沙警方
They sent for the Santa Rosa police.
那又能怎样？
What good will they do?
凯西在学校没问题吧？
Do you think Cathy's all right at the school?
我确定她很安全
Yes, I'm sure she's fine.
觉得我很可笑吗？
Do I sound very foolish to you?
不
Oh, no.
我一直看见丹的脸
I keep seeing Dan's face.
学校里有很大的窗户
And they have such big windows at the school.
丹房间里的窗户全破了
All the windows are broken in Dan's bedroom.
- 全部的窗户！ - 别再想那些了
All the windows! Try not to think about that.
我真希望我能坚强一点
I wish I were a stronger person.
四年前，我失去丈夫
I lost my husband four years ago, you know.
这糟透了 依赖别人给力量
It's terrible how you depend on someone else for strength, and then
但这力量突然间没了 独留一人
suddenly all the strength is gone, and you're alone.
我希望偶尔也能放松
I'd love to be able to relax sometime.
我希望能睡得着
I'd love to be able to sleep.
- 凯西不会出事吧？ - 有安妮在
Do you think Cathy's all right? Annie's there.
她没事的
She'll be all right.
我通常不会这样
I'm not like this, you know? Not usually.
我不会处处担心我的孩子
I don't fuss and fret about my children.
法兰克去世后…
When Frank died...
他生前很了解孩子们 非常了解他们
You see, he understood the children. He really understood them.
他就是有办法进到他们的世界 成为他们的朋友
He had the knack of entering into their world and becoming part of them.
- 那是很厉害的本事 - 是
That's a very rare talent. Yes.
我真希望能像他一样
Oh, I wish, I wish, I wish I could be like that.
我好想他
I miss him.
即使到了现在 我偶尔早上醒来还会想着
Sometimes, even now, I wake up in the morning and I think,
“我得替法兰克煮早餐”
"I must get Frank's breakfast."
接着我起身 这是让人起床的大好理由
And I get up, and there's a very good reason for getting out of bed,
直到
until, of course,
我记起来
I remember.
我想念跟他聊天
I miss talking to him.
凯西还是个孩子，而米契…
Cathy's a child, of course, and Mitch...
米契有自己的生活
Well, Mitch has his own life.
我很高兴他今天留下来
I'm glad he stayed here today.
有他在我安心多了
I feel safer with him here.
- 想休息了吗？ - 不
Would you like to rest now? No.
不，别走
No, don't go.
我觉得我一点都不了解
I feel as if I don't understand you at all,
但我想好好认识
and I want so much to understand.
为什么？
Why, Mrs. Brenner?
因为我儿子似乎很喜欢
Because my son seems to be very fond of you,
而我不知道我做何感想
and I don't quite know how I feel about it.
我甚至不知道我喜不喜欢
I don't even know if I like you or not.
喜欢我有那么重要吗？
Is that so important, your liking me?
我是这么想的
Well, yes. I think so.
米契对我来说很重要
Mitch is important to me.
我想喜欢他选上的女孩
I want to like whatever girl he chooses.
如果不喜欢呢？
And perhaps if you don't?
那么除了我以外 对任何人来说都无所谓
Well, then I don't think it'll matter very much to anyone but me.
我想米契也会在意的
Oh, I think it would also matter to Mitch.
米契总是照自己的意思行事
Mitch has always done exactly what he wanted to do.
但是我不想被抛弃
But, you see, I don't want to be left alone.
我无法忍受被抛弃！
I don't think I could bear to be left alone!
原谅我
Oh, forgive me.
鸟杀人的事让我好心烦
This business with the birds has upset me.
如果米契不在 我真不知道该怎么办
I don't know what I'd do if Mitch weren't here.
班纳太太，何不试着睡一下？
Why don't you try to sleep now, Mrs. Brenner?
我希望我能坚强点
I wish I was stronger.
觉得她会没事吗？
Do you think she's all right?
她在学校里不会有事吧？
Do you think she's all right at the school?
- 要我去接她吗？ - 我不能这样要求
Would you like me to go for her? Oh, I couldn't ask it.
- 我不介意，真的 - 是吗？
Oh, I don't mind, really. Would you?
- 我感觉好多了 - 我现在就去
I'd feel so much better. I'll go right now.
梅兰妮？
Melanie?
谢谢的茶
Thanks for the tea.
I married my wife in the month of June
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Now, now, now
I brought her home by the light of the moon
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
She combs her hair but once a year
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Now, now, now
With every stroke She shed a tear
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Rustical quality Ristle-tee, rostle-tee
Now, now, now
I brought her home by the light of the moon
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
She combed her hair but once a year
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Now, now, now
With every stroke She shed a tear
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
She swept up her floor but once a year
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Now, now, now
She said that brooms were much too dear
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
She churns the butter in her dad's old boot
Ristle-tee, Rostle-tee Now, now, now
And for a dash She'd use her foot
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
The butter it came out all grizzle-y gray
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Now, now, now
The cheese it took legs and ran away
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
She let the critter get away
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
I asked my wife to wash the floor
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Now, now, now
She gave me my hat and she showed me the door
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Now, now, now
I married my wife in the month of June
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Now, now, now
I brought her home by the light of the moon
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
She combed her hair but once a year
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Hey, donnie-dostle-tee
Knickety-knackety Rustical quality
Willow-tee, wallow-tee Now, now, now
Ristle-tee, rostle-tee Now, now, now
好了，孩子们 请把歌本收起来
All right, children. Now, please put your song books away,
站在你们的桌子边
then stand up alongside your desks.
等大家准备好 我们就到外面去玩
We'll go out for recess as soon as everybody gets ready.
等大家安静下来
We are not going into the playground
我们才要去游乐场
until everybody has quieted down.
- 快点把门关上 - 什么？
- Close that door. Quickly. Please. - What?
- 怎么了？ - 看
- What is it? - Look.
我们得把孩子们带离学校
We've got to get the children out of here.
好了，孩子们，安静
All right, children. Now, quiet.
丹尼尔斯小姐想看看
Quiet. Miss Daniels would like to see
我们进行防火演习的样子
how we conduct ourselves during a fire drill.
请你们让她见识一下 你们有多安静、多听话
I would like you to show her how quiet and obedient you can be.
- 我们现在要离开学校了 - 离开学校？
Oh, we're going out of school now. Leave school?
住在附近的人 我们要你们直接回家
We want those of you who live nearby to go directly home.
回家？
Home?
其他的人则一路跑到 山下的旅馆，听清楚了吗？
I want the rest of you to go down the hill all the way to the hotel. Now, is that clear?
是，海沃斯老师
Yes, Miss Hayworth.
梅兰妮？
Melanie?
我要大家安静地离开
I want you to go as quietly as possible.
在我要你们跑之前 不准出声音
Do not make a sound until I tell you to run.
跑得越快越好 大家都听懂了？
Then run as quickly as you can. Now, does everybody understand?
懂了，海沃斯老师
Yes, Miss Hayworth.
约翰，由你带头
All right, John, you lead the way.
凯西！
Cathy! Cathy!
爸爸，有好几百只鸟
Well, Daddy, there were hundreds of them.
我没有歇斯底里
No, I'm not hysterical.
我试着尽可能冷静地向你解释
I'm trying to tell you this as calmly as I know how.
好吧，是，爸爸
All right, Daddy. Yes, Daddy.
就是刚才，不是15分钟前
Well, just now. Not 15 minutes ago.
在学校
At the school.
不，我没有，等等 学校叫什么名字？
No, I don't. Just a minute. What's the name of the school?
- 博德加湾学校 - 博德加湾学校
Just the Bodega Bay School. The Bodega Bay School.
我不知道有多少学生 30或40个吧
Well, I don't know how many children, 30 or 40.
不，学生出了学校 鸟才开始攻击
No, the birds didn't attack until the children were outside the school.
- 邦迪太太，需要什么？ - 我要换零钱，卡特先生
Help you, Mrs. Bundy? I need some change, Mr. Carter.
应该是乌鸦
Crows, I think.
我不知道
Well, I don't know, Daddy.
乌鸦跟黑鸟有什么差别吗？
Is there a difference between crows and blackbirds?
- 差别可大了，小姐 - 谢谢
There is very definitely a difference, miss. Thank you.
它们是不同的鸟，爸爸
They're different, Daddy.
我认为这些是乌鸦
Well, I think these were crows.
对，好几百只
Well, yes. Hundreds of them.
它们攻击孩子，攻击他们！
Yes, they attacked the children. Attacked them!
我不知道何时 但我现在走不开，爸爸
Well, I don't know when, but I simply can't leave now, Daddy.
好，再见
All right. Yes. Good-bye.
它们都属雀形目，但品种不同
They're both perching birds, of course, but quite different species.
乌鸦的学名为短嘴鸦
The crow is Corvus brachyrhynchos,
黑鸟的学名则是蓝头黑鹂
and the blackbird is Euphagus cyanocephalus.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 你有佛西特农场的电话吗？ - 这本册子上有
You have the number at the Fawcett farm? Right here in this book, miss.
邦迪太太 我认为是乌鸦或是黑鸟
I can't see that it makes any difference, Mrs. Bundy.
都没有差别
Crows or blackbirds,
如果它们攻击学生 那事态就严重了
if the school was attacked, that's pretty serious.
我认为这两种鸟
I hardly think that either species
都没有足够的智慧 能发动一场集体攻击
would have sufficient intelligence to launch a massed attack.
它们的头颅太小…
Their brainpans are not big enough to...
我刚从学校过来，女士
I just came from the school, madam.
我对它们的头颅一无所知，但…
I don't know anything about their brainpans, but...
但我知道
Well, I do. I do know.
我正好对鸟类学有兴趣
Ornithology happens to be my avocation.
鸟类不是凶猛的生物
Birds are not aggressive creatures, miss.
它们为这世界增色 反而是人类…
They bring beauty into the world. It is mankind, rather, who...
山姆！三份南方炸鸡
Sam! Three southern fried chicken.
全搭配烤马铃薯
Baked potato on all of them.
请找米契班纳
Yes, may I speak to Mitch Brenner, please?
好，我等
Yes, I'll wait.
反而是人类坚持要
It is mankind, rather, who insists upon
让生物难以活在地球上
making it difficult for life to exist upon this planet.
- 如果没有鸟类… - 邦迪太太，不明白
Now, if it were not for the birds... Mrs. Bundy, you don't seem to understand.
这位小姐说学生被鸟攻击了
This young lady said there was an attack on the school.
- 不可能！ - 米契？
- Impossible! - Oh, Mitch?
好险我找到你了
Oh, I'm glad I caught you.
- 可怕的事… - 世界末日到了！
Something terrible has... It's the end of the world!
两杯血腥玛丽，迪克
Two Bloody Marys, Deke.
学校出了什么事？
What actually happened at the school?
有一群乌鸦攻击学生
Bunch of crows attacked the school kids.
世界末日到了 因此主耶和华
It's the end of the world. "Thus saith the Lord God
对高山、丘陵、河流和山谷
"unto the mountains and the hills, "and the rivers and the valleys.
说道
"Behold I, even I,
我必让你们遭遇刀害
"shall bring a sword upon you,
“我必摧毁你们的邱坛”
"and I will devastate your high places."
以西结书第六章
Ezekiel, chapter six.
灾祸降临于清早起床
"Woe unto them that rise up early in the morning,
“就追求烈酒之人”
"that they may follow strong drink."
以赛亚书第五章 世界末日到了
Isaiah, chapter five. It's the end of the world.
我不认为 几只鸟会造成世界末日
I hardly think a few birds are going to bring about the end of the world.
- 这不是几只鸟而已 - 我不知道博德加湾
These weren't a few birds. I didn't know there were many crows in Bodega Bay
在这个时节会有这么多乌鸦
this time of year.
乌鸦会固定留在它的栖息地里
The crow is a permanent resident throughout its range.
事实上，在圣诞节期间 我们计算过有…
In fact, during our Christmas count, we recorded...
邦迪太太 你们算过有多少只海鸥？
How many gulls did you count, Mrs. Bundy?
休尔斯先生，哪种海鸥？ 海鸥有分很多种
Which gulls, Mr. Sholes? There are several varieties.
危害我渔船的那种
The ones who've been playing devil with my fishing boats.
- 海鸥也给你带来麻烦？ - 上周攻击我的一艘船
Have you had trouble with gulls? One of my boats did, last week.
这位小姐周六才被海鸥攻击
This young lady was hit by a gull only Saturday.
迪克，我还在等血腥玛丽
Deke, I'm still waiting for those Bloody Marys.
马上来
Coming right up.
能否请他们小声点？
Could you ask them to lower their voices, please?
他们吓到孩子了
They're frightening the children.
一大群海鸥几乎弄翻了我的船
A whole flock of gulls nearly capsized one of my boats.
差点扯下船长的手臂
Practically tore the skipper's arm off.
- 你吓到孩子了，小声点 - 好
You're scaring the kids. Keep it low. All right.
他也吓到我了
Yeah, well, he's scaring me, too.
你的意思是这些…
Are you trying to say that all these...
不，这不可能，赛巴斯汀
Nah, that sounds impossible, Sebastian.
迪克，我只是说出 我的船遇到什么事
Deke, look, I'm just telling you what happened to one of my boats.
海鸥想要你船上的鱼，休尔斯先生
The gulls were after your fish, Mr. Sholes.
请你用点逻辑
Really, let's be logical about this.
那攻击学生的乌鸦呢？
What were the crows after at the school?
认为它们想要什么？ 是…
What do you think they were after? Miss...
丹尼尔斯 我想它们要的是孩子们
Daniels. I think they were after the children.
目的呢？
For what purpose?
- 杀了他们 - 为什么？
To kill them. Why?
我不知道原因
I don't know why.
我不这么认为
I thought not.
丹尼尔斯小姐，自始祖鸟开始
Birds have been on this planet, Miss Daniels,
鸟类在一亿四千万年前 就出现在地球上
since Archaeopteryx, 140 million years ago.
它们等了那么久 才跟人类宣战
Doesn't it seem odd that they'd wait all that time
不是有点奇怪吗？
to start a war against humanity?
- 没人说这是战争 - 威士忌加水
No one called it a war. Scotch, light on the water.
跟休尔斯先生 似乎就是这个意思
You and Mr. Sholes seem to be implying as much.
谁说到战争了？ 我只是说有海鸥…
Who said anything about a war? All I said, some gulls...
- 再来点咖啡？ - 不了
- Want some more coffee? - No.
…攻击我的船
...came down on one of my boats.
如所说的 它们要的可能是鱼
They could have been after the fish, just like you said.
船长应该要射死它们
- The Captain should have shot at them. - Huh?
海鸥是食腐动物 多数的鸟类都是
Gulls are scavengers, anyway. Most birds are.
拿起枪 让它们在地球上消失吧！
Get yourselves guns and wipe them off the face of the Earth!
- 那是不可能的 - 为什么？
That would hardly be possible. Why not, Mrs. Bundy?
因为当今世界上
Because there are 8,650 species
有8650种鸟类，卡特先生
of birds in the world today, Mr. Carter.
光是美国估计就有
It is estimated that 5,750,000,000 birds
五十七亿五千万只鸟
live in the United States alone.
世界五大洲…
The five continents of the world...
杀光它们！ 除掉这些麻烦的动物
Kill them all. Get rid of the messy animals.
…可能就有超过一千亿只鸟
...probably contain more than 100 billion birds.
- 世界末日到了 - 那些海鸥一定是想吃鱼
It's the end of the world. Those gulls must have been after the fish.
- 当然！ - 孩子们，快把饭吃完
Of course! Hurry up, children. Finish your lunch.
妈妈，鸟会吃掉我们吗？
Are the birds gonna eat us, Mommy?
我们也许太过小题大做了
Hell, maybe we're all getting a little carried away by this.
几只鸟确实很反常 但没理由相信…
Admittedly, a few birds did act strange, but that's no reason to believe that...
我说过了，这不止是几只鸟 有海鸥、乌鸦、雨燕…
I keep telling you, this isn't a few birds. These are gulls, crows, swifts...
我没听说过 不同种类的鸟会聚集在一起
I have never known birds of different species to flock together.
那是无法想像的
The very concept is unimaginable.
如果真的发生了 我们根本没机会！
Why, if that happened, we wouldn't have a chance!
我们怎么可能斗得过它们？
How could we possibly hope to fight them?
我们不可能赢 说得对，邦迪太太
We couldn't, you're right. You're right, Mrs. Bundy.
发生什么事了？
What's the matter? Something wrong out here?
我们正在打仗，山姆
We're fighting a war, Sam.
打仗？ 跟谁打？
A war? Against who?
- 跟鸟打！ - 真庆幸你们以为这很有趣
Against birds! I'm glad you all think this is so amusing.
你们快把孩子们吓死了
You've frightened the children half out of their wits.
若这位小姐说
If the young lady said
她看见学生被攻击 你们为何不相信她？
she saw the attack at a school, why don't you believe her?
- 攻击？ 谁攻击学生了？ - 鸟、乌鸦
What attack? Who attacked the school? Birds did. Crows.
你们只顾着争辩！
You're all sitting around here debating!
你们想它们接下来会怎样？ 撞破窗户？
What do you want them to do next? Crash through that window?
- 妈妈！ - 外套穿上
Mommy! Shh. Put on your coat.
你们何不回家把门窗锁好？
Why don't you all go home, lock your doors and windows?
- 到旧金山最快的路线是？ - 高速公路，女士
What's the fastest way to San Francisco? The freeway, ma'am.
怎么走？
How do I find it?
我也要去高速公路 可以跟着我
I'm going out that way, lady. You can follow me.
- 那我们马上走吧 - 我的酒还没喝完
Well, then let's leave now. Haven't finished my drink yet.
我尽快赶来了，凯西在哪里？
I got here as fast as I could. Where's Cathy?
- 她跟安妮在一起，她没事 - 艾尔，学生被攻击时
She's with Annie. She's all right. Al, why aren't you over at the school,
你怎么没赶到学校？
where the attack was?
因为我刚刚人在丹佛西特家
'Cause I just got back from Dan Fawcett's place, that's why.
- 他昨晚被鸟杀死了 - 什么？
He was killed last night by birds. What?
慢着，米契，你还不能确定
Now, hold it, Mitch. You don't know that for a fact.
马龙先生，事实是什么？
What are the facts, Mr. Malone?
圣塔罗沙警方认为是重罪谋杀
The Santa Rosa Police think it's a felony murder.
他们认为是小偷闯进去杀了他
They think a burglar broke in, killed him.
那满地的死鸟又该如何解释？
How do you explain the dead birds all over the floor?
圣塔罗沙警方认为 鸟是在他被杀害后才飞进来的
Santa Rosa Police figure they got in after the old man was killed.
圣塔罗沙警方 今天有到学校去吗？
Were the Santa Rosa Police at your school today?
- 你要来吗？ - 冷静点，女士
Are you coming? Now take it easy, lady.
这里看不见一只鸟！
There isn't a bird anywhere in sight!
看看天上的鸟 它们不播种也不收获
"Look at the birds of the air. They do not sow or reap.
“但你们的天父喂养它们”
"Yet your heavenly Father feeds them."
圣塔克鲁兹 去年也发生了这种事
Say, something like this happened in Santa Cruz last year.
海鸥遮盖了整座城镇
The town was just covered with seagulls.
- 请快把你的酒喝完 - 没错，我想起来了
Will you please finish your drink? That's right, sir. I recall it.
一大群海鸥在雾中迷路
A large flock of seagulls got lost in a fog,
朝着光线飞进了镇上
and headed into the town where all the lights were.
那也造成了不少麻烦 冲进建筑物里之类的
They made some mess, too, smashing into buildings and everything.
鸟就会制造麻烦
They always make a mess.
重点是没人为此感到不满
The point is that no one seemed to be upset about it.
它们隔天早上就离开了 好像什么事都没发生一样
They were all gone next morning, just as though nothing at all had happened.
- 可怜的东西 - 我要走了！你来不来？
Poor things. I'm leaving! Are you coming?
来了！
All right, all right!
希望你们能搞清楚这件事！
Well, hope you folks figure this thing out!
世界末日到了！
It's the end of the world!
我该回罐头工厂了 迪克，多少钱？
I better get back to the cannery. What do I owe you, Deke?
赛巴斯汀，等一下
Sebastian, hold it a minute.
- 我不想大惊小怪… - 没人说你是，米契
I don't want to be an alarmist about this... No one ever said you were, Mitch.
我想我们麻烦大了 我不知道这件事的起因
I think we're in real trouble. I don't know how this started, or why,
但我知道这是真的 我们不能不管
but I know it's here and we'd be crazy to ignore it.
- 不管什么？  “鸟的战争”？ - 对，“鸟的战争”
To ignore what? The "bird war"? Yes, the "bird war."
鸟类攻击、瘟疫… 随怎么称呼
The bird attack, plague... Call it what you like,
它们正在某处聚集 它们会回来的，我敢保证
they're massing out there someplace, and they'll be back. You can count on it.
- 荒谬 - 过来一下
Ridiculous. Come here.
除非我们采取行动
Unless we do something right now,
除非我们疏散博德加湾…
unless we get Bodega Bay on the move, they...
听着，米契
Look, Mitch.
就算这是真的，就算这些鸟…
Even if this is true, even if all the birds...
- 你不相信这是真的？ - 米契，我不相信
Don't you believe it's true? No, Mitch, frankly I don't.
- 这没道理… - 这确实发生了，还没道理吗？
There's no reason. I... Well, it's happening. Isn't that a reason?
- 我爱博德加湾… - 那就协助我
I like Bodega Bay as well as the next man... Fine, then help me.
你是镇上的要人 若你帮我，镇民都会听话
You're an important man in this town. If you help, they all will.
怎么帮？ 你想怎么做？
Help how? What do you want to do?
邦迪太太提到圣塔克鲁兹的事
Mrs. Bundy said something about Santa Cruz.
海鸥在雾中迷路 朝着光线飞去
About seagulls getting lost in a fog and flying in towards the lights.
- 这时节不会起雾！ - 那就用人工造雾！
We don't have fog this time of year! Make our own fog!
要怎么做？
How do you figure to do that?
学军队使用烟雾罐
We can use smoke pots, the way the Army uses them.
你们看！
Look!
它们又攻击了 梅兰妮，待在这里，走吧，艾尔！
They're attacking again. Melanie, you stay in here. Come on, Al!
小心！
Look out!
汽油流了满地 那个男人在点烟！
Look at the gas. That man's lighting a cigar!
嘿！听着！别把火柴丢地上！
Hey, you! Watch out! Don't drop that match!
快离开！
Get out of there!
- 先生，快跑！ - 小心！
- Mister, run! - Watch out!
注意！小心啊！
Look out! Look out! Watch out!
嘿！
Hey!
它们为什么要这么做？
Why are they doing this?
别人说在来了之后 整件事就开始了！
They said when you got here, the whole thing started!
是谁？ 是什么东西？
Who are you? What are you?
从哪里来的？
Where did you come from?
我认为这都是造成的
I think you're the cause of all this.
我想是恶魔！恶魔！
I think you're evil! Evil!
天啊！
Oh, God!
它们离开了！
I think they're going!
我们可以去安妮家接凯西了
We can get Cathy at Annie's now.
乌鸦又来了
- The crows again. - Shh!
走吧
Come on.
不，待在这里
Oh, no. Stay here. Stay here.
凯西！凯西在哪里？
Cathy! Where's Cathy?
米契，住手！
Mitch, don't!
别把她留在那里，米契
Oh, don't leave her there, Mitch.
走吧
Come on.
我们送蜜雪儿回家后
When we got back from taking Michele home,
我们听见了爆炸声
we heard the explosion
我们就到外头查看
and we went outside to see what it was.
鸟一下子聚集过来！
All at once the birds were everywhere!
她急忙把我推进屋里
All at once she pushed me inside,
鸟盖在她身上！
and they covered her!
安妮…她把我推进屋里！
Annie... She pushed me inside!
再给我一片木板
Give me another one, darling.
它们在那边聚集多久了？
How long have they been gathering there?
大概15分钟
Oh, about 15 minutes.
这似乎有个模式
Seems like a pattern, doesn't it?
它们攻击之后就消失 接着再开始聚集
They strike, then disappear, and then start massing again.
看起来没什么不同，对吧？
Doesn't look so very different, does it?
像一阵烟笼罩着镇上…
A little smoke hanging over the town, otherwise...
要再联络父亲吗？
You want to try your father again?
不，我刚刚试过了 电话不通
No, I tried a little while ago. The phone's dead.
- 但我们还有电力吧？ - 有
- Still got power, haven't we? - Yes.
米契，电台传出消息了
Mitch, I'm getting something on the radio.
走吧
Come on.
我收不到当地电台
I can't get any of the local stations.
这应该是旧金山的电台
I think this is San Francisco.
“…和一组专业团队” 结束
"...and the work of a team of professionals." End quote.
今早在博德加湾 有一大群乌鸦
In Bodega Bay early this morning, a large flock of crows
攻击因防火演习 而正在离校的学生
attacked a group of children who were leaving the school during a fire drill.
一位女孩因此受到重伤 被送往圣塔罗沙的医院
One little girl was seriously injured and taken to the hospital in Santa Rosa,
但多数学生都很平安
but the majority of children reached safety.
我们收到镇上 还有另一起攻击事件
We understand there was another attack on the town,
但资讯还不完全
but this information is rather sketchy.
到目前为止 还没有消息指出
So far, no word has come through
是否还有更多攻击事件
to show if there have been further attacks.
今日的国内新闻，华盛顿…
On the national scene today, in Washington...
就这样？
Well, is that all?
我得再拿些木头进来 绝不能让火熄灭
I'll have to get some more wood in. Mustn't let this fire go out.
- 米契，你有封死阁楼的窗户吗？ - 都封好了
Did you get the windows in the attic, Mitch? Yes, I got them all, dear.
- 你觉得它们何时会攻击？ - 我不知道
When do you think they'll come? I don't know.
若有更大型的鸟 它们会冲进屋子里的
If there are bigger birds, Mitch, they'll get into the house.
- 我们只得冒这个险 - 也许我们该离开
Well, it's just a chance we'll have to take. Maybe we ought to leave.
现在不行！ 它们正在外头聚集
No, not now! Not while they're massing out there.
- 那要何时？ - 我们再看看
When? We'll just see what happens.
- 我们要去哪？ - 我不知道
- Where will we go? - I don't know.
目前我们很安全
I think we're safe here for the time being.
- 我们去捡木头 - 木头烧光了怎么办？
Let's get the wood in now. What happens when you run out of wood?
- 我不知道！我们可以拆家具 - 你不知道！
I don't know! We'll break up the furniture. You don't know!
你何时才会知道？ 到时我们都死了！
You don't know! When will you know? When we're all dead!
如果你爸在的话…
If only your father were here...
对不起，米契
I'm sorry. I'm sorry, Mitch.
去煮点咖啡喝，好吗？
Make yourself some coffee, won't you?
在假定总统的任务时
"In assuming the tasks of the presidency,
“我认为少有世代…”
"I said that few generations..."
- 它们要去哪里？ - 内陆某处
Where are they heading? Somewhere inland.
- 圣塔罗沙？ - 也许吧
Santa Rosa? Maybe.
走吧，我们去捡木头
Come on. Let's get the wood.
- 米契，我能把爱情鸟拿进来吗？ - 不行！
Mitch? Can I bring the lovebirds in here? No!
- 妈妈，它们在笼子里 - 它们也是鸟，不是吗？
But, Mom, they're in a cage. They're birds, aren't they?
让它们待在厨房吧，亲爱的
Let's leave them in the kitchen, huh, honey?
米契，鸟为什么要这么做？
Mitch, why are they doing this, the birds?
- 我们不知道，亲爱的 - 它们为什么要杀人？
We don't know, honey. Why are they trying to kill people?
我希望我知道原因
I wish I could say.
我不太舒服，梅兰妮
I'm sick, Melanie.
- 我想… - 我陪去
I want to... I'll go with you.
它们走了
They're going.
米契？
Mitch?
米契！
Oh, Mitch!
带凯西和莉迪雅离开这里
Get Cathy and Lydia out of here.
梅兰妮！
Melanie! Melanie!
Melanie!
可怜的东西！
Oh, poor thing! Poor thing!
去拿点水 绷带和消毒药水过来，快！
Listen, get some water, bandages, and antiseptic. Quickly!
绷带，太可怕了
Bandages. It's terrible.
凯西，拿白兰地过来
Cathy, get some brandy.
别怕！没事了
No, no, no! No, no, it's all right.
好了，没事了
No, it's all right, it's all right, it's all right.
没事了
It's all right. It's all right. No.
凯西，拿油灯过来
Cathy, get the lamp.
我们得送她去医院
We've got to get her to a hospital.
- 不行，我们没地方可去 - 旧金山
We can't, Mitch. There's no place we can go. There's San Francisco.
- 我们撑不到那里 - 我们得试试
We'd never make it. We have to try.
我们走海湾山路 就不必穿过镇上了
We'll go by way of Bay Hill Road. Then we don't have to go through town.
我们不能待在这里 她需要帮助！
We can't stay here. She needs help!
我好怕，非常害怕
I'm frightened. Terribly frightened.
我不知道外面有什么东西
I don't know what's outside there.
我们最好在 下次攻击到来之前出发
We better get started before another attack comes.
我们开梅兰妮的车 那会比开卡车快
We'll take Melanie's car. That'll be faster than the truck.
- 能替她包扎好吗？ - 我尽量
Can you finish the bandaging? I'll try.
好
All right.
米契？ 用车上的收音机 听听有什么消息
Mitch? See if you can get anything on the car radio.
鸟类攻击事件目前已缓和
The bird attacks have subsided for the time being.
博德加湾似乎是攻击的中心 虽然赛巴斯托波和圣塔罗沙
Bodega Bay seems to be the center, though there are reports of minor attacks
也传出了轻微的攻击事件
on Sebastopol and a few on Santa Rosa.
博德加湾周围已设满路障
Bodega Bay has been cordoned off by roadblocks.
多数的镇民已设法逃出
Most of the townspeople have managed to get out,
但仍有少数居民受困
but there are still some isolated pockets of people.
至于下一步该怎么做 当局还没有决定
No decision has been arrived at yet as to what the next step will be,
但已有人开始讨论 是否该派军队进驻
but there's been some discussion as to whether the military should go in.
鸟类攻击似乎是阵歇性的
It appears that the bird attacks come in waves,
中间的间隔时间很长
with long intervals between.
攻击原因目前还不明朗
The reason for this does not seem clear as yet.
你有从电台上听到什么吗？
Did you hear anything on the radio?
没关系，来吧
It's all right. Come on.
不，不要！
No. No!
米契？
Mitch?
待在那里
Stay there.
米契，我能带爱情鸟走吗？
Can I bring the lovebirds, Mitch?
它们没有伤害人
They haven't harmed anyone.
(subtitle from http://shooter.cn by SPlayer1216
好吧，带着它们
All right. Bring them.
(subtitle from http://shooter.cn by SPlayer